P: So, Janice, what’s your take on the book?
J: Thanks, Sam. Well, this is a very interesting book.
According to the authors, helicopter parents are a combination of strict and supportive.
They have high expectations about what their children should achieve,
both academically and in their general lives,
but they are also available to talk to them and give them help when they need it.
This is very different from authoritarian parents
– the so-called tiger parents – who put a big emphasis on obedience.
P: And what do the authors say is the main benefit of helicopter parenting?
J: Well, the main benefit of this type of parenting is in academic achievement.
There are several studies that prove that children of helicopter parents get the highest exam results
– regardless of background, they achieve higher scores in maths, reading, and science
– and these children are also very likely to go on to university.
P: So, how does this compare with other types of parenting? How do their children do?
J: Well, apparently, children of free-range parents get the second-highest results,
followed by children of tiger parents.
P: Which is interesting,
because people normally think that children of tiger parents get the top results!
So, what kinds of things do helicopter parents do with their children
that make such a difference to academic performance?
J: Well, reading with children, telling them stories, and, when they are older, discussing politics:
these are all things which they say push up test scores significantly, and, apparently,
doing all three regularly can account for a huge increase in test scores.
But, in fact, they do say that it’s not so much the specific activity that makes a difference,
it’s more that these parents are closely engaged with their children.
They give them lots of attention – the right sort of attention.
P: And they’re also very keen on extracurricular activities: the music lessons, the sports, and so on.
Do they make a difference, too?
J: Yes. Well, helicopter parents commonly insist
that their children learn an instrument or a foreign language, or do a sport.
This is significant, the authors say,
because certain types of extracurricular activities have an important influence on a child’s development.
For example, encouraging a child to play the violin or piano is not just for the pleasure of music:
it also trains them to focus better on a task.